Finding Aid for Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan records, 1830-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Diocesan staff
  - Office of The Record
    - Photographs, 1850, 1924, 1940-1980, 1960-1980
      The Photographs (1850, 1924 and 1940-2000) sub-subseries is further divided into three sub-sub-subseries: People, Topical, and Churches. The People sub-sub-subseries contains photographs of individual bishops, clergy, laymen, laywomen and deaconesses. The files are arranged alphabetically by the individual's last name. Most of the files contain at least one formal or informal photograph of each individual. Many of the bishops and clergy are also shown participating in church activities. A few files contain paper materials associated with individuals, such as resumes and ordinations programs. Photographs of church activities, church meetings, social programs and member's community activism are found in the Topical sub-sub-subseries. The files are arranged alphabetically. The sub-sub-subseries Churches is comprised the diocese's churches and the activities related to their ministries. A majority of the photographs are interior and exterior images of the churches. Many files also contain photographs of the clergy who served in these churches. Paper materials related to church activities and programs can be found in several of the files. The files in this sub-subseries are arranged alphabetically by the city in which the church is located.
      - People 1850, 1940-2000 (bulk, 1960-1980)
        - Bishops
          - Bishops A-G (Box 17)
          - Charles Braidwood (archdeacon) (Box 17)
          - Archie Crowley (suffragan bishop) (Box 17)
          - Edmond L. Browning (Photographs of Browning with U.S President George Bush (1989), Pope Paul II (1987), Bishop Desmond Tutu of South Africa) and papers. (Box 17)
          - Robert Lionne DeWitt, photographs and papers (Box 17)
          - Richard Emrich, photographs and papers (Box 17)
          - William Gordon, (Missionary Bishop of Alaska) (Box 17)
          - Frank Griswold (Box 17)
          - John L. Hines (Box 17)
          - Henry Irving Mayson, photographs and papers (Box 17)
          - Samuel J. McCoskry (Box 17)
          - Harry Coleman McGehee (photographs and papers) (Box 17)
          - C. Kilmer Myers (Box 17)
          - R. Steward Wood Jr (Box 17)
          - Various groupings (Box 17)
        - Clergy, Deaconessess, Laymen and Laywomen
          - A-C, 3 folders (Box 17)
          - D-E (Box 18)
          - Deaconesses (Box 18)
          - F-G (Box 18)
          - H, 2 folders (Box 18)
          - Bill Hale, photographs and papers 1992-1993 (Box 18)
          - I-K, 2 folders (Box 18)
          - Richard Kim, photographs and papers 1987-1988, 1990 (Box 18)
          - L (Box 18)
          - Laymen and Laywomen (Box 18)
          - M, 2 folders (Box 18)
          - Kilmer Myles, photographs and papers 1964, 1966 (Box 18)
          - N-T, 5 folders (Box 18)
          - Almus M Thorp, Jr., photographs and papers 1993 (Box 18)
          - W-Z, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Topical Files 1970-1990s
        - Abortion, Operation Rescue demonstration undated (Box 18)
        - Aids and healing ministry 1990s (Box 18)
        - Aging ministry (no date) (Box 18)
        - All Saints, food distribution, Pontiac undated (Box 18)
        - Anti-Hunger and Youth Rally (St. Columba) 1983 (Box 18)
        - Assisting Kosovo Refugees 1999 (Box 18)
        - Basketball League 1991 (Box 18)
        - Blessing the animals undated (Box 18)
        - Camp Chickagami (Box 18)
        - Camp Holiday undated (Box 18)
        - Canterbury on the Lake, Eden Alternative activity undated (Box 18)
        - Crosswords 1981, 1983-1984 (Box 18)
        - Detroit Newspaper Strike -- Bishop Wood arrested undated (Box 18)
        - Emrich Conference Center undated (Box 18)
        - Eucharist Service and Demonstrations at Williams International 1985 (Box 18)
        - General Convention, Detroit 1988 (Box 18)
        - Gordonwood Camp and Conference Center 1990s (Box 18)
        - Herlong Cathedral School 1983, 1985 (Box 18)
        - Mariner's Inn, shelter undated (Box 19)
        - Pontiac Area Transitional Housing (PATH) undated (Box 19)
        - Shepard House 1990 (Box 19)
        - Soup Kitchens undated (Box 19)
        - South Oakland Shelter, rotating shelter for homeless 1987 (Box 19)
        - St. Anne's Mead, retirement home 1966 (Box 19)
        - St. Christopher's House 1980s (Box 19)
        - St. Luke's Episcopal Church Home 1970s (Box 19)
        - St. Peter's Alternative School for Girls 1989 (Box 19)
        - St. Peter's Home for Boys 1970s (Box 19)
        - Urban Caucus (Detroit 1980-1981); Urban Caucus National Board Meetings 1980; Summer Urban Programs, Urban Misc. (Box 19)
        - Venture in Missions 1979, 1980, 1981 (Box 19)
        - Walk for Lighthouse 1983, 1985 (Box 19)
        - Williams Pavilion, senior housing 1986 (Box 19)
      - Churches 1924, 1950-1990s 1960-1980
        - Adrian, Christ Church (Box 19)
        - Ann Arbor, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Bay City (Box 19)
        - Belleville (Box 19)
        - Birmingham (Box 19)
        - Bloomfield Hills (Box 19)
        - Bridgeport (Box 19)
        - Brighton (Box 19)
        - Cambridge (Box 19)
        - Chelsea (Box 19)
        - Chesaning (Box 19)
        - Clinton (Box 19)
        - Clawson (Box 19)
        - Dearborn (Box 19)
        - Detroit, 20 folders (Box 19)
        - Dewitt (Box 19)
        - Dexter (Box 19)
        - Dryden (Box 19)
        - Drayton Plains (Box 19)
        - East Detroit (Box 19)
        - East Lansing (Box 19)
        - Ecorse (Box 19)
        - Farmington Hills (Box 19)
        - Ferndale (Box 19)
        - Fraser (Box 19)
        - Garden City (Box 19)
        - Grosse Ile (Box 19)
        - Grosse Pointe (Box 19)
        - Grosse Pointe Woods (Box 19)
        - Hamburg (Box 19)
        - Harbor Beach (Box 19)
        - Harsens Island (Box 19)
        - Hazel Park (Box 19)
        - Highland Park (Box 19)
        - Hillsdale (Box 19)
        - Howell (Box 19)
        - Inkster (Box 19)
        - Jackson (Box 19)
        - Jonesville (Box 19)
        - Lake Orion, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Lansing, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Livonia, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Lincoln Park (Box 19)
        - Mason (Box 19)
        - Monroe (Box 19)
        - Michigan Center (Box 19)
        - Mt. Clemens (Box 19)
        - Mt. Morris (Box 19)
        - Novi (Box 19)
        - Omer (Box 19)
        - Orchard Lake (Box 19)
        - Otter Lake (Box 19)
        - Pittsfield (Box 19)
        - Pleasant Lake (Box 19)
        - Plymouth (Box 19)
        - Pontiac (Box 19)
        - River Rouge (Box 19)
        - Rochester (Box 19)
        - Royal Oak (Box 19)
        - Saint Clair Shores (Box 19)
        - Saline (Box 19)
        - Southfield, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Southgate (Box 19)
        - Saint Clair (Box 19)
        - Saint Johns (Box 19)
        - Standish (Box 19)
        - Taylor (Box 19)
        - Tecumseh (Box 19)
        - Trenton (Box 19)
        - Troy (Box 19)
        - Utica (Box 19)
        - Warren (Box 19)
        - Williamston (Box 19)
        - Wyandotte (Box 19)
- Parishes and missions
  The Parishes and missions series contains two subseries, Collected church materials and Church files. Collected Church Materials includes such documents as church histories, deeds and mortgages, correspondence, clippings, and information about the church building, mainly from the 19th century through the first half of the 20th century. The Church Files, 1974-1994 (some to 1997) consists of correspondence, memos, publications, and some photograph maintained by diocesan staff and officers for individual parishes and missions. Most of the files in this series relate to churches that were transferred to the Diocese of Eastern Michigan in 1995, while a few relate to churches that were closed during the time period of the series. Additional church files are found in the Archdeacon William Logan subseries (boxes 10-11).
  - Collected church materials
    - Allen Park, Alpena, Alma (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor (includes history prepared for sesquicentennial), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Au Sable, Bad Axe, Bay City, Beechville, Belleville, Big Rapids (Box 2)
    - Birmingham, Bridgehampton, Brighton, Brooklyn (Box 2)
    - Cambridge Junction, Carsonville, Cheboygan, Clinton (Box 2)
    - Coldwater, Corunna (including Owosso, Ovid and St. Johns), Dearborn (Box 2)
    - Detroit
      - Christ Church (Box 2)
      - Detroit Clericus (Box 2)
      - Epiphany (Box 2)
      - Good Shepherd (Box 2)
      - Grace (Box 2)
      - Incarnation (Box 2)
      - Mariners Church (Box 2)
      - St. Andrew's (Box 2)
      - St. George's (Box 2)
      - St. James (Box 2)
      - St. John's (Box 2)
      - St. Mark's (Box 2)
      - St. Matthew's (Box 2)
      - St. Matthias (Box 2)
      - St. Paul's (Box 2)
      - St. Peter's (Box 2)
      - St. Philip's (Box 2)
      - St. Stephen's (Box 2)
      - St. Thomas (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Dexter, East Tawas, Escanaba (Box 2)
    - Ferndale (Box 2)
    - Flint (Box 2)
    - Gagetown, Gladstone, Grass Lake, Grosse Isle, Hamburg, Harsen's Island (Box 2)
    - Hazel Park, Henrietta, Highland Park, Hillman, Hillsdale, Houghton Lake (history prepared for sesquicentennial), Howell (Box 2)
    - Hudson (Box 2)
    - Jackson, Jonesville, Lapeer, Linden, Long Rapids (Box 2)
    - Mackinac Island, Marine City, Marlette (Box 2)
    - Menominee, Monroe, Mount Clemens, Oakley Park, Otter Lake, Port Crescent, Port Huron, River Rouge, Rochester (Box 2)
    - Romeo, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Romulus, Royal Oak (Box 2)
    - Saginaw
      - General (Box 2)
      - Report 1961 of the General Division of Research and Field Study of the National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church, entitled "A Study of the Episcopal Church in the City of Saginaw, Michigan" (Box 2)
    - St. Clair, St. Louis, Sandusky, Sault Ste. Marie, South Norwood, Stockbridge (Box 2)
    - Tecumseh, Vassar, Wayne (Box 2)
    - Wyandotte, Ypsilanti (Box 2)
  - Church files 1974-1994 (some to 1997)
    - Algonac St. Andrew's (Box 36)
    - Alma St. John's (Box 36)
    - Bad Axe St. Paul's (Box 36)
    - Alpena Trinity (Box 36)
    - Atlanta St. Mark's (Box 36)
    - Bay City St. Alban's (Box 36)
    - Bay City Trinity (Box 36)
    - Bridgeport St. Mark's (Box 36)
    - Burton St. Christopher's (Box 36)
    - Canton All Saints (Box 36)
    - Cheboygan St. James (Box 36)
    - Chesaning St. John's (Box 36)
    - Corunna St. Paul's (Box 36)
    - Croswell-Lexington Trinity (Box 36)
    - Davison St. Dunstan's (Box 36)
    - Dearborn Heights Good Shepherd (Box 36)
    - Detroit Ascension (Box 36)
    - Detroit Epiphany (Box 36)
    - Detroit Incarnation (Box 36)
    - Detroit Our Saviour (Box 36)
    - Detroit St. Andrew's Memorial (Box 36)
    - Detroit St. James (Box 36)
    - Detroit St. Matthias (Box 36)
    - Detroit St. Thomas (Box 36)
    - Dryden St. John's (Box 36)
    - Durand St. John's (Box 36)
    - East Tawas Christ Church (Box 36)
    - Fair Haven All Saints (Box 37)
    - Fenton St. Jude's (Box 37)
    - Flint Christ Church (Box 37)
    - Flint St. Andrew's (Box 37)
    - Flint St. Paul's (Box 37)
    - Flushing Trinity (Box 37)
    - Forester St. Peter's (Box 37)
    - Gaylord St. Andrew's (Box 37)
    - Gladwin St. Paul's (Box 37)
    - Grayling St. Francis (Box 37)
    - Harbor Beach St. Margaret's (Box 37)
    - Harrisville St. Andrew's (Box 37)
    - Harsens Island St. Paul's (Box 37)
    - Highland Park Alexander Crummell Memorial (Box 37)
    - Highland Park St. Alban's (Box 37)
    - Higgins Lake St. Elizabeth's (Box 37)
    - Hillman Calvary (Box 37)
    - Holly St. John's (Box 37)
    - Houghton Lake All Saints (Box 37)
    - Indian River Transfiguration (Box 37)
    - Lapeer Grace (Box 37)
    - Linden St. Bede's (Box 37)
    - Long Rapids Grace (Box 37)
    - Marine City St. Mark's (Box 38)
    - Marysville All Saints (Box 38)
    - Midland Holy Family (Box 38)
    - Midland St. John's (Box 38)
    - Mio St. Bartholomew's (Box 38)
    - Omer St. Thomas (Box 38)
    - Oscoda St. John's (Box 38)
    - Otter Lake St. John's (Box 38)
    - Owosso Christ Church (Box 38)
    - Oxford Lake Orion St. Alfred's (Box 38)
    - Port Austin St. John's (Box 38)
    - Port Huron Grace (Box 38)
    - Port Huron St. Paul's (Box 38)
    - Rogers City St. Luke's (Box 38)
    - Rose City St. Andrew's (Box 38)
    - Saginaw Calvary (Box 38)
    - Saginaw St. John's (Box 38)
    - Saginaw St. Matthew's (Box 38)
    - Saginaw St. Paul's (Box 38)
    - St. Clair St. Paul's (Box 38)
    - St. John's St. John's (Box 38)
    - Sand Point St. John's (Box 38)
    - Sandusky St. John's (Box 38)
    - Standish Grace (Box 38)
    - Swartz Creek St. Bartholomew's (Box 38)
    - Temperance St. John's (Box 38)
    - Thomas Township Holy Spirit (Box 38)
    - [The remainder of the alphabet was not received] (Box 38)
- Clergy
  The Clergy series currently contains one subseries. The Clergy Biographical File includes two kinds of records: one is listing of the assignments of former clergy, including dates and places for ordinations and transferals. There is also occasional information such as date of birth and college and university where educated. The second set of records - clergy profile update - is for the year 2000 only and consists of information about current clergy within the diocese.
  - Clergy Biographical Files
    - Former Clergy of the Diocese, A-Z, 4 volumes (Box 23)
      (arranged alphabetically)
    - Clergy Update forms 2000, 2 volumes (Box 24)
- Audio and Visual Material
  The Audio and Visual series includes photographs, sound recordings, videotapes, a film, and a slide show. The Photograph subseries consists of images of church personalities and church buildings.
  - Photographs
    - Activities
      - Archbishop of Canterbury visit 1967 (Box 16)
      - Batchelder Hall (Box 16)
      - Camp Chickagami (Box 16)
      - Camp Frisbie (Box 16)
      - Consecration of Bishop Aldrich May 4, 1945 (Box 16)
      - Gay Liberation Front protest at diocesan convention 1970s (Box 16)
      - Women's protest at Bishop Emrich's office 1970s (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Churches
      - Alpena County (Alpena, Lachine, Long Rapids) (Box 16)
      - Arenac County (Standish) (Box 16)
      - Bay County (Bay City) (Box 16)
      - Cheboygan County (Cheboygan) (Box 16)
      - Clinton County (St. Johns) (Box 16)
      - Genesee County (Fenton, Flint) (Box 16)
      - Gladwin County (Gladwin) (Box 16)
      - Gratiot County (Alma) (Box 16)
      - Hillsdale County (Hillsdale, Jonesville) (Box 16)
      - Huron County (Bad Axe) (Box 16)
      - Ingham County (Lansing, Williamston) (Box 16)
      - Iosco County (Au Sable, East Tawas) (Box 16)
      - Isabella County (Coleman) (Box 16)
      - Jackson County (Brooklyn, Jackson) (Box 16)
      - Lapeer County (Dryden, Lapeer, Otter Lake) (Box 16)
      - Lenawee County (Adrian, Cambridge, Hudson) (Box 16)
      - Livingston County (Brighton, Hamburg, Howell, Parishfield) (Box 16)
      - Mackinac County (Mackinac Island, Point aux Pins) (Box 16)
      - Macomb County (Roseville) (Box 16)
      - Monroe County (Monroe) (Box 16)
      - Montmorency County (Hillman) (Box 16)
      - Oakland County (Birmingham, Bloomfield Hills, Ferndale, Hazel Park, Pontiac, Rochester, Royal Oak) (Box 16)
      - Ogemaw County (Rose City, West Branch) (Box 16)
      - Presque Isle County (Hagensville, Onaway) (Box 16)
      - Roscommon County (Houghton Lake) (Box 16)
      - Saginaw County (Chesaning, Saginaw) (Box 16)
      - St. Clair County (Algonac, Marine City, Port Huron, St. Clair) (Box 16)
      - Sanilac County (Croswell, Lexington, Marlette) (Box 16)
      - Shiawassee County (Corunna, Durand, Owosso) (Box 16)
      - Washtenaw County (Ann Arbor, Dexter) (Box 16)
      - Wayne County (Dearborn, Grosse Pointe, Inkster, Lincoln Park, Plymouth, Wayne, Wyandotte) (Box 16)
      - Detroit
        - Ascension, Emmanuel, Messiah, Redeemer, St. Barnabas, St. Columba's (Box 16)
        - St. Cyprian's, St. James', St. John's, St. Joseph's, St. Mark's (Box 16)
        - St. Martin's, St. Mary's, St. Matthew's, St. Matthias' (Box 16)
        - St. Paul's Cathedral, St. Paul's Memorial (Box 16)
        - St. Peter's, St. Philip and St. Stephen, St. Thomas', St, Timothy's, Trinity (Box 16)
        - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 16)
    - People
      - Bishops
        - McCoskry, Harris, Davies (Box 16)
        - Page, Creighton (Box 16)
        - Emrich (Box 16)
        - McGehee (Box 16)
        - Wood (Box 16)
      - Clergy (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous people (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Group portraits (Folder 1)
      (in UBAl and Ba Outsize folders)
    - Photograph of Bishop Frank Creighton (Folder 2)
      (in Ba Outsize folder)
    - Gordonwood Camp, camper and staff photographs (Folder 3)
    - Gordonwood Camp, camper and staff photographs (Box 1)
  - Sound recordings
    - Sound recording 1958 concerning the history of St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Ferndale, Michigan, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 1)
    - Convention addresses, consecration and ordination services, etc. 1958, 1990s, 23 audiocassettes; 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 1)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - "From the Past into the Future: The Dioceses of Michigan" 1994 (Box 1)
      3 versions
    - Address to Diocesan Convention by the Rt. Rev. Stewart Wood, Jr. 1990 (Box 1)
    - St. Paul's (Lansing) Jubilee 2000 Celebration, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Rt. Rev. Wendell Gibbs, Jr. special message (Box 1)
    - Bishop Frank Tracy Griswold's investiture January 10, 1998, 2 tapes (Box 1)
    - Gordonwood Camp, 2 tapes (Box 1)
    - "Diocese of Michigan Venture in Mission" 1981, 16 mm film (Box 1)
    - "Venture in Mission" (slide show with cassette produced by Diocese of Michigan) (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series contains materials brought together from a variety of sources that were not a part of a larger set of files .The Historical Information subseries contains histories of the dioceses, collected biographical material about bishops and other individuals important to the church. The Topical Files subseries is a grouping of files from different sources primarily from the period of the 1980s and 1990s. Of special interest are files relating to the church's response to the "Black Manifesto" (1968-1970). There are also depositions and other legal briefs pertaining to the Diocese's dispute with Mariners' Church. The Scrapbook subseries dates from 1943 to 1962. The six volumes consist mainly of clippings about diocesan activities and personalities.
  - Topical files (from various sources)
    - Bishops' convention addresses 1974-1996 (some gaps) (Box 21)
    - Bishops' memorial service programs (Box 21)
    - Black Manifesto 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Detroit Council of Churches miscellanea (Box 21)
    - Division of the Diocese of Michigan 1994 (Box 21)
      (creation of the Diocese of Eastern Michigan)
    - Emrich (Bishop Richard) miscellanea (Box 21)
    - Homosexuality report 1973 (Box 21)
    - Long Range Goals 1980 (Box 21)
    - Mariners' Church 1955-1993, 0.5 linear feet (Box 21)
      (general papers and litigation materials)
    - Mariners' Inn (Box 21)
    - Marriages (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Parish charters and incorporation (Box 21)
    - Parishes of the Diocese (Box 21)
      (groundbreaking and other programs)
    - Parishes of the Diocese (Box 22)
      (church histories, and miscellaneous)
    - Raising Up of Episcopal Leadership manual 1997 (Box 22)
    - Seal and Flag of Diocese (Box 22)
    - Transition Committee 1998-2000 (Box 22)
    - Urban Mission Planning Committee 1967-1969 (Box 22)
    - Walters (Jennifer) ordination controversy 1994 (Box 22)
    - WPA, Historical Records Survey, history of diocese miscellanea 1939-1940 (Box 22)
    - Williams (Bishop Charles D.); research paper written by Carlson Gerdau entitled, "Bishop Charles D. Williams: Inspiration of Reinhold Niebuhr" 1987 (Box 22)
    - Wood (Bishop R. Stewart, Jr.) program celebrating his ministry (Box 22)
    - [processing note-box not full] (Box 22)
  - Historical Information
    - Histories
      - Episcopal church in Michigan, by C.O. Ford undated (Box 22)
      - Diocese of Michigan, by Gilbert Appelhof 1927, undated (Box 22)
      - Diocese of Michigan, by Rev. Luther B. Moore 1949, 3 folders (Box 22)
      - Episcopal Church in Michigan undated, 3 folders (Box 22)
      - Recollections of Missionary Work Among Blacks in the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan 1936-1972 by Malcolm G. Dade, D.D. (Box 22)
      - Diocese of Marquette undated (Box 22)
      - Papers 1933-1951 and undated, concerning the history of the Diocese of Michigan, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Historical material 1983 regarding 150th Anniversary of the Michigan Diocese (Box 22)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated 1830-1884 (Box 22)
      - 1900-1939 (Box 22)
      - 1940-1959 (Box 22)
    - Biographical Material
      - A-D (concerning James V. Campbell, James F. Conover, Frank W. Creighton, Thomas F. Davies, and William L. Davis) 1833-1939 (Box 22)
      - H-M (concerning Samuel S. Harris, Andrew Jamison, William Lyster, Sidney D. Miller, and Julia H. Mills) 1888-1948 (Box 22)
      - P-W (concerning Herman Page, James E. Pittman, Charles C. Trowbridge, Alanson W. Welton, and Charles D. Williams) 1883-1942 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 1885-1951 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1943-1950 (Volume 2)
    - 1950-1957 (Volume 3)
    - 1955-1956 (Volume 4)
    - 1959-1960 (Volume 5)
    - 1960-1961 (Volume 6)
    - 1961-1962 (Volume 7)